<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<democratic_debate>COOPER: Senator Sanders, I want to bring it over to Juan Carlos Lopez from CNN en Espanol. We're obviously in Nevada. It's had the highest percentage of <trope status="illegal" term="undocumented immigrant">undocumented immigrants </trope>of any state in the country as of last year. Juan Carlos?

LOPEZ: Gracias, Anderson. Senator Sanders, in 2013, you voted for <trope type="legislature" status="neutral">immigration reform</trope>. But in 2007, when Democrats controlled Congress and the Bush White House was onboard, you voted against it. Why should Latino voters trust you now when you left them at the altar at the moment when reform was very close?

SANDERS: I didn't leave anybody at the altar. I voted against that piece of legislation because it had guest-worker provisions in it which the Southern Poverty Law Center talked about being semi-slavery. <trope status="legal" type="economic" subtype="job" term="gues_worker">Guest workers</trope> are coming in, they're working under terrible conditions, but if they stand up for their rights, they're thrown out of the country. I was not the only progressive to vote against that legislation for that reason. Tom Harkin, a very good friend of Hillary Clinton's and mine, one of the leading labor advocates, also voted against that.

LOPEZ: Tom Harkin isn't running for president. You are.

SANDERS: I know that. But point being is that progressives did vote against that for that reason. My view right now — and always has been — is that when you have 11 million <trope status="illegal" term="undocumented_people">undocumented people</trope> in this country, we need comprehensive <trope type="legislature" status="neutral">immigration reform</trope>, we need a path toward citizenship, we need to take <trope status="illegal" term="people" type="legislature" subtype="citizenship">people</trope> out of the shadows.

O'MALLEY: And Juan Carlos — Juan Carlos...

LOPEZ: Secretary Clinton — Secretary Clinton, Governor O'Malley wants to open up Obamacare to millions of <trope status="illegal" type="economic" subtype="healthcare" term="undocumented_immigrant">undocumented immigrants</trope> and their children, including almost 90,000 people right here in Nevada. Do you?

CLINTON: Well, first of all, I want to make sure every child gets health care. That's why I helped to create the Children's Health Insurance Program, and I want to support states that are expanding health care and including <trope status="illegal" term="undocumented_children" type="legislature" subtype="healthcare">undocumented children</trope> and others.

I want to open up the opportunity for <trope status="legal" type="legislature" subtype="healthcare" term="immigrant">immigrants</trope> to be able to buy in to the exchanges under the Affordable Care Act. I think to go beyond that, as I understand what Governor O'Malley has recommended, so that they would get the same subsidies.

I think that is — it raises so many issues. It would be very difficult to administer, it needs to be part of a comprehensive <trope status="neutral" type="legislature">immigration reform</trope>, when we finally do get to it.

LOPEZ: Governor O'Malley?

O'MALLEY: Juan Carlos, I think what you've heard up here is some of the old thinking on <trope status="neutral" type="legislature">immigration reform</trope>, and that's why it's gridlocked. We need to understand that our country is stronger in every generation by the arrival of new American <trope status="legal" type="legislature" subtype="citizenship" term="immigrant">immigrants</trope>. That is why I have put out a policy for comprehensive <trope status="neutral" type="legislature">immigration reform</trope>, that is why I would go further than President Obama has on DACA, and DAPA.

I mean, we are a nation of <trope status="legal" term="immigrant" type="nationalism">immigrants</trope>, we are made stronger by <trope status="legal" term="immigrant" type="nationalism">immigrants</trope>. Do you think for a second that simply because somebody's standing in a broken que on <trope type="legislature" subtype="citizenship">naturalization</trope> they're not going to go to the hospital, and that care isn't going to fall on to our insurance rates? I am for a generous, compassionate America that says we're all in this together. We need comprehensive

COOPER: Senator Webb...

O'MALLEY: ...<trope type="legislature" status="neutral">immigration reform</trope>. It'll make wages go up in America $250 for every year...

LOPEZ: Senator Webb, do you support the <trope type="econ" subtype="healthcare" status="illegal" term="undocumented_immigrant">undocumented immigrants</trope> getting Obamacare?

WEBB: I wouldn't have a problem with that. Let me start by saying my wife is an <trope type="anecdote" status="legal" term="immigrant">immigrant</trope>. She was a <trope status="legal" term="refugee" type="anecdote">refugee</trope>, her family escaped from Vietnam on a boat-- her entire extended family, after the communists took over, when hundreds of thousands of people were out there and thousands of them were dying. Went to two refugee camps, she never spoke English in her home, and she ended, as I said, graduating from Cornell Law School. That's not only <trope type="nationalism" subtype="values">American dream</trope>, that's a value that we have with a good immigration system in place. No country has — is a country without defining its <trope type="home_sec" subtype="borders">borders</trope>. We need to resolve this issue. I actually introduced an amendment in the 2007 <trope type="legislature">immigration bill</trope>...

LOPEZ: ...Thank you, Senator.

WEBB: ...Giving a pathway to citizenship to those people who had come here, and put down their roots, and met as a series of standards...

COOPER: ...Thank you, Senator.

WEBB: ...lost (ph) — I introduced that in 2007 — We need a comprehensive reform, and we need to be able to define our <trope type="home_sec" subtype="borders">borders</trope>.

COOPER: Secretary Clinton?

CLINTON: I want to follow up because I think underneath Juan Carlos' important questions, there is such a difference between everything you're hearing here on this stage, and what we hear from the Republicans. [applause]

O'MALLEY: Here. Here.

(CHEERING) (APPLAUSE)

CLINTON: Demonize hard-working <trope term="immigrant" status="legal" type="econ" subtype="job">immigrants</trope> who have insulted them. You know, I came to Las Vegas in, I think, May. Early may. Met with a group of <trope status="neutral" type="nationalism" subtype="values" term="dreamer">DREAMers</trope>, I wish everybody in America could meet with this young people, to hear their stories, to know their incredible talent, their determination, and that's why I would go further...

COOPER: ...Secretary...

CLINTON: ...than even the executive orders that President Obama has signed when I'm president.

(CROSS TALK)

COOPER: Secretary Clinton, let me ask you. Two of your rivals from your left, Governor O'Malley, and Senator Sanders, want to provide instate college tuition to <trope term="undocumented_immigrant" status="illegal" type="econ" subtype="school">undocumented immigrants</trope>. Where do you stand on that?

CLINTON: My plan would support any state that takes that position, and would work with those states and encourage more states to do the same thing.

COOPER: So, on the record, you believe that <trope term="undocumented_immigrant" status="illegal" type="econ" subtype="school">undocumented immigrants</trope> should get instate college tuition.

CLINTON: If their states agree, then we want more states to do the same thing.

COOPER: Governor O'Malley?

O'MALLEY: Anderson, we actually did this in my state of Maryland. We passed... [applause]

O'MALLEY: We passed a state version of the DREAM Act...

(CHEERING)

O'MALLEY: ...And a lot of the xenophobes, the <trope status="legal" term="immigrant">immigrant</trope> haters like some that we've heard like, Donald Trump, that carnival barker in the Republican party...

(CHEERING) (APPLAUSE)

O'MALLEY: Tried to mischaracterize it as free tuition for illegal <trope term="immigrant" status="illegal" type="econ" subtype="school">immigrants</trope>. But, we took our case to the people when it was petitioned to referendum, and we won with 58 percent of the vote. The more our children learn, the more they will earn, and that's true of children who have yet to be <trope type="legislature" subtype="citizenship">naturalized</trope>...

COOPER: ...Senator...

O'MALLEY: ...but will become American citizens...</democratic_debate>
